<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Catherine Cree Church, upon Sunday the 29th of June, 1696 by Nicholas Brady ... ; published at the desire of the parishioners.</title>
            <author>Brady, Nicholas, 1659-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37129</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16219563</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16219563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1088:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Catherine Cree Church, upon Sunday the 29th of June, 1696 by Nicholas Brady ... ; published at the desire of the parishioners.</title>
                  <author>Brady, Nicholas, 1659-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 28.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XX, 32 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at St Catherine Cree Church, UPON <hi>Sunday</hi> the 29th of <hi>June,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <p>By <hi>NICH. BRADY,</hi> M.A. Miniſter of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> in the County of <hi>Surry,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Deſire of the Pariſhioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rich. Parker,</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> under the Piazza of the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105122:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105122:2"/>
            <head>To my worthy Friends, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Select and General Veſtry, and others the Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of <hi>St. Catherine Cree-Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS this Farewel Sermon was not barely intended for a ſolemn for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality upon quitting my employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but was the reſult of ſentiments both tender and ſerious, expreſſed with all imaginable ſincerity and heartineſs; ſo I flatter my ſelf with the Belief, that your deſiring me to make it publick, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a ceremonious Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being a freſh inſtance of that kindneſs and good will, with which you have always been pleas'd to favour me.</p>
            <p>And therefore, however fairly I might excuſe my ſelf, by the plainneſs and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtedneſs of the following Diſcourſe; yet I cannot refuſe you the abſolute di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſal
<pb facs="tcp:105122:3"/>of that which is ſo juſtly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely your own; and ſhall pleaſe my ſelf with the agreeable opinion, That <hi>your Affection to me</hi> is the cauſe of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing,</hi> what <hi>my Affection to you</hi> was the occaſion of <hi>Compoſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That you may ſtill continue <hi>ſtedfaſt and immoveable</hi> in the profeſſion of that Faith which I have preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, and <hi>always abound in that Work of the Lord,</hi> to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of which I have conſtantly exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you; that ſo, neither <hi>my Labour in</hi> Preaching, nor yours in practiſing, <hi>may be in vain in the Lord;</hi> ſhall be the earneſt and continual Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obliged Friend, and moſt humble Servant,</hi> N. Brady.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105122:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ACTS XX. 32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And now Brethren, I commend you to God, and to the word of his Grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an Inheritance among all them which are ſanctified.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THough it is not without a very ſenfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concern, that I appear before you upon the preſent occaſion, that I find my ſelf ſo near being ſeparated from thoſe, with whom I have convers'd in five years Miniſtry, and from whom I have receiv'd ſuch obliging inſtances of affection, as ſhall ever be precious to my memory; yet ſince neither the reſpect I ſo juſtly owe you, nor the deference we pay to a prevailing cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, will ſuffer me to wave the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly task, of taking a ſolemn and publick
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105122:4"/>leave. I thought I could not more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addreſs to you, than in theſe words of the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles. They are a part of <hi>his farewel Sermon,</hi> which he made to the Elders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Miletus, among whom he had gone preaching the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God:</hi> He foreſaw that this would be their laſt meeting, and that <hi>they to whom he ſpake ſhould ſee his face no more,</hi> and therefore thought himſelf obliged to transfer the care of them, to him who was beſt able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and defend them; and to commit the guidance of them to that Goſpel of his, which was both capable of eſtabliſhing them in the truth, and of intitling them to that reward which is the conſequence of it: <hi>and now Brethren</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I commend you to God and to the word of his Grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an inheritance, among all them which are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God, the circumſtances of our parting, are not ſo diſmal as thoſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle and his friends; inſtead of <hi>not ſeeing one anothers faces</hi> any more; I truſt we ſhall have many happy opportunities, of keeping
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105122:4"/>up a mutual correſpondence and intimacy: However, ſince providence has thought fit to withdraw me, from the more immediate care of the ſpiritual concernments, I cannot better expreſs my ſollicitude for your welfare, I cannot conſign you into bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hands, than by <hi>commending you to God</hi> for favour and protection, and <hi>to the word of his Grace</hi> for counſel and inſtruction.</p>
            <p>And here I muſt entreat that you would not expect from me, a diſcourſe that is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodical and artificial, that is the reſult uſually of well compos'd thoughts, not the product of a mind under diſturbance and perplexity: I ſhall only take the words juſt as they lye before me, and expound them to you with all the plainneſs imaginable, and</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>my Brethren, I commend you to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever dangers may at any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm you, whatſoever apprehenſions or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions you may lye under, if you have but recourſe to an all-ſufficient Guardian, if you find your ſelves intitled to his favour and protection, you have then got ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge as will never fail you, but will enable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105122:5"/>you in all difficulties <hi>to be more than conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</hi> Can any condition be ſuppoſed ſo miſerable, wherein the eye of a <hi>father</hi> will not look upon you? can any eſtate be ſo wretchedly forlorn, wherein the bowels of a <hi>Redeemer</hi> will not yearn over you? can any circumſtances be ſo deplorable, as to ſet bounds to a goodneſs which is infinite? can any of thoſe friends whoſe aſſiſtance you may value, whoſe ſupport and ſuccour you may depend upon, produce ſuch evidences of their kindneſs towards you, or ſhew ſuch ſtrong credentials of an unalterable affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as thoſe which you have received from your almighty benefactors. Was it not he who drew you out of the dark womb of nothing? is it not in him that <hi>you live and move and have your being?</hi> has not his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful providence continually watched over you? are you not indebted for whatever you enjoy, to him that <hi>is the giver of every good and perfect gift?</hi> has not his goodneſs been exerted wonderfully in your behalf, and magnified its ſelf by moſt remarkable mercies? does not he compaſſionate all your
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105122:5"/>neceſſities, favourably accept of your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect performances kindly overlook your manifold infirmities, and patiently bear with your groſſer provocations? is he not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be reconciled whenſoever you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him? not ready to caſt you off in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, upon every the leaſt tranſgreſſion of your duty? but waiting for your ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with gentleneſs and long-ſuffering, and opening his arms wide to the returning pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent? and how then can you wiſh for a more affectionate Protector? to whoſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs can I recommend you more juſtly than to his? but farther, have not his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and his power been frequently exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in ſecuring you againſt all the malice of your enemies, whether in private ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems or open violences? is it not he <hi>that brings the counſel of the heathen to nought, and makes the devices of the people of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect?</hi> is it not he <hi>that does whatſoever pleaſes him, in heaven and in earth, and in all deep places?</hi> Can any thing fruſtrate or diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point his intentions, <hi>with whom all Wiſdom is for ever?</hi> or pretend to oppoſe the irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105122:6"/>force of him that is <hi>girded about with ſtrength?</hi> Has he not many times unravel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the ſecret deſigns, which your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triguing Adverſaries had levelled againſt you; and turned the <hi>wiſdom of their wiſe men into fooliſhneſs?</hi> Has he not often baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled and defeated all their boaſted might, <hi>with his own right hand, and with his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arm?</hi> Has not he over-ruled the moſt unlikely events, and made <hi>all things work together to you for good?</hi> Either obvia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all inconveniences by his wiſe diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, or elſe overcoming them by his powerful aſſiſtance? And how then can you deſire a more available Guardianſhip? To whoſe conduct can I reſign you more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely than to His? Can the care of your ſafety be better conſulted than by him, who is not only your beſt of friends, but the moſt fitly qualified for exerciſing that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? Can the ſumm of your concerns be more aſſuredly repoſed, than upon bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Wiſdom and unlimited Power? Such is the Protector to whoſe patronage <hi>I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you,</hi> diſpoſed by his Goodneſs, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105122:6"/>by his Wiſdom, and enabled by his Power, to ſupport and ſuſtain you under the greateſt exigencies, and to give you a happy iſſue out of all your adverſities. May then that God, whoſe mercy is over all his works, whoſe knowledge is unfathomable by humane Reaſon, and whoſe power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to be glorified in our weakneſs be your merciful Saviour and mighty Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer; may he be your firm ſupport in all extremities, your conſtant refuge in all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, your certain comfort in all cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; and as he influenced you by his good Spirit, to thoſe offices of love which I have received at your hands, ſo may he reward all the kindneſs you have ſhewn me ſeven fold into your own boſomes. This will God moſt aſſuredly perform; unleſs you render yourſelves uncapable of the ſweet refreſhings of his goodneſs, by not paying a due obedience to his commands, nor walking by the rule which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes; and therefore, my brethren, <hi>I commend you</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105122:7"/>2dly, <hi>To the word of his Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>was given by</hi> Moſes, <hi>but Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The Goſpel is a moſt comfortable conveyance of the divine love and favour to us; it is a Covenant made up of mercy and tenderneſs, free from all the burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom hardſhips and uneaſineſſes, with which the legal diſpenſation was clogg'd and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumber'd: In this God ſeems to have laid aſide his abſolute prerogative, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult at once the eaſe and the delight of his ſervants; the bloody initiation of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is exchanged for the milder Sacrament of Baptiſm; expenſive Sacrifices are aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that prayers and praiſes may ſucceed them, and the dreadful menace, of draw <hi>not near leſt I conſume thee,</hi> is turned into the obliging invitation, of <hi>come unto me and I will give you reſt.</hi> Well then may a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of ſuch comfortable importance, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be ſtiled <hi>the word of his Grace,</hi> ſince it exhibits to us the moſt gracious promiſes, it holds forth to us the moſt deſireable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, it preſcribes the moſt reaſonable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105122:7"/>meaſures of obedience, and the moſt eaſy methods of reconciliation. By this we are allowed to recover our ſelves, when through humane frailty we at any time fall, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtate our ſelves in the favour of our God, and regain our forfeited intereſt by a ſincere repentance; by this we are adopted into his own family, and put on the character of his Favourites and Sons; by this we are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a free acceſs, to a kind of intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and familiarity with our God; by this we are made capable of celeſtial entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of <hi>taſting the powers of the world to come.</hi> Theſe are ſome of thoſe ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble priviledges, of that <hi>word of Gods Grace to which I commend you;</hi> and I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign you over to any thing more valuable, but to what I have already, even to God himſelf. I exhort you therefore to adhere carefully to thoſe admirable rules which it lays down for your direction; to attend heedfully to the leſſons which it gives; to make that the ſtandard of all your actions, and to let your whole converſation be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to that model. The excellency of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105122:8"/>the doctrines which it would eſtabliſh, is enough to recommend it to any prudent conſiderer; what can more conſiderably exalt your nature, than that univerſal puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which it preſcribes? what can more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually preſerve Society, than that impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Juſtice which it exacts? what can more ſecure your health and vigour, than that ſtrict temperance which it requires at your hands? what can more promote mutual amity and concord, than that obliging be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity which it would infuſe into your natures? Thus if you would but examine the Doctrines which it contains, you would find it to deſerve your moſt ſerious obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. But if you farther reflect upon the perſon that delivered it, you will find freſh arguments for the fixing it in your eſteem: <hi>God who in times paſt ſpake to your fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe later days ſpoken unto you by his Son;</hi> who being <hi>the brightneſs of his glory, and the expreſs I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his perſon,</hi> deſerves your attention to what he delivers, more than any other perſon of a leſs elevated quality. <hi>I ſay unto
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105122:8"/>you,</hi> is his conſtant form of ſpeaking, with which he uſhers in his moſt weighty inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; and a due contemplation of the majeſty of the Speaker, ſhould make you attend to what he utters with a becoming reverence and reſpect. Again, the vaſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of the things imparted in it, ſhould forcibly oblige you to value it as you ought: This explains to you the nature and the attributes of God, and ſhews you <hi>his way of dealing with the ſons of men;</hi> this gives you a proſpect into the inviſible world, and makes you acquainted with that land of ſpirits; it ſhews you by what methods God will diſpence his unconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable rewards or puniſhments; and gives you directions by which you may be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to ſecure to your ſelves the former, and to avoid the latter: the mighty mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therefore of the matters which it treats of, is ſufficient to engage you to an awful attention; but farther yet, the inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate concern which you your ſelves have in thoſe ſacred truths which the Goſpel unfolds to you, ſhould powerfully engage
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105122:9"/>you to give heed to its directions: it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains no account of foreign news or idle tranſactions, to which you may either liſten or turn a deaf ear, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable conſequences to your ſelves; but rules for the management of your own lives and converſations; precepts which exact your own obedience; your own intereſt is at ſtake in every part of it; and an eternal portion of happineſs or miſery will be your own lot, according as your application to the duties it enjoins, is more or leſs ſerious and conſiderate: The immediate depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance therefore which you have, upon that <hi>word of Grace</hi> to which <hi>I commend you,</hi> ſhould abundantly perſwade you to pay a due regard to it. Theſe are ſome of thoſe ſtrong and conſiderable motives, which I hope will incline you to put a juſt value upon the maxims and inſtructions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to inſtance in ſome <hi>peculiar</hi> duties in <hi>general,</hi> which I would recommend more particularly to your practice and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance; and the firſt that I ſingle out ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105122:9"/>be <hi>Humility,</hi> becauſe it is the neceſſary prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative for all other graces and perfections of the ſoul: Repreſs, I beſeech you, all unnatural ſwellings of the mind, all extravagant opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of your own ſelf-ſufficiency, copy the example of your Saviour and <hi>learn of him, for he was meek and lowly in heart:</hi> avoid that Pride which was a tempter even to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil himſelf; which changed that brighteſt created reſemblance of the Deity, into a loathſom and deteſted Fiend: This it was that loſt us Paradice, and expoſed the whole race of miſerable mankind to the heavy wrath of an offended God; but as by Pride the humane nature fell, ſo by Humility it roſe again; and what was loſt by the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> was regain'd by the condeſcenſion of the ſecond. Let then this grace be your darling favourite, let it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be your boſom jewel, which tho here it may look meanly, like a Diamond in the Ore, yet will ſhine hereafter with an amazing luſtre, and be the brighteſt ornament of your immortal Diadem. Another Grace in which I muſt entreat you to be converſant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105122:10"/>is <hi>Charity;</hi> I mean that part only of this comprehenſive duty, which is employed in relieving the neceſſities of ſuch as want. Forfeit not, I conjure you, that well deſerv'd Commendation of being one of the moſt charitable Pariſhes within the City; keep up that Diſtinction above moſt others, which your large Contributions upon any ſignal occaſion have given you by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all Unprejudiced Obſervers. This is a vertue ſo amiable in its ſelf, that the pleaſure which reſults from its perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, were enough to make any one enamour'd of it, though no other reward were conſequent upon it; and therefore it is hard to find a Man who has once been charitable, and ceaſed afterwards to be ſo: the very ſatisfaction which ariſes from the action, being ſufficient to retain him in the practice of it; and yet ſuch is the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Almighty God, that he has affixt rewards both temporal and eternal, to that which is ſo amply its own recompence: this will <hi>cover a multitude of your faults,</hi> and caſt a veil over your numerous tranſgreſſions;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105122:10"/>this will give a value to all your other good deeds, which <hi>without charity are nothing worth:</hi> this is that by which you muſt be tried and ſentenced in the great and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day of the Lord, and this is that only which will accompany you to heaven, and make up a part of your everlaſting felicity. Let this then be your conſtant entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let it be made your buſineſs, as it will be your delight, and it will liken you to the Angels, who ſtill miniſter to our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, and reſemble you to your Saviour, who <hi>went about doing good.</hi> A third duty to which I ſhall more eſpecially exhort you, is <hi>Peace.</hi> Remove (I adjure you) all that bitterneſs of ſpirit which is wont to incline people to quarrels and animoſities; let all narrow diſtinctions be done away of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and of Factions, and converſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with brotherly affection, under the comprehenſive characters of Men and Chriſtians. Bear with one anothers errors and infirmities, endeavour to overcome with meekneſs and affability, and never to exaſperate with ſowreneſs and reproaches:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105122:11"/>This is an obliging temper of mind, which <hi>will make even your enemies to be at peace with you,</hi> and will ſhame them into kindneſs and condeſcenſion; <hi>if a Brother be overtaken in a fault,</hi> whether it be an error in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or in practice, <hi>reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſs, and if it is poſſible as much as in you lies live peaceably with all men;</hi> avoid all malicious invectives and back-bitings, all reflecting ſtories and ill-natur'd raillery; and endeavour by your favourableſt and moſt charitable conſtruction to make the beſt of one anothers failings; ſo will you find by a happy experience, <hi>how good and pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in unity,</hi> and will have a title to thoſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which attend it, <hi>for there God has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his bleſſing and life for evermore</hi> Let this then be at once your employment and your pleaſure, and it will poſſeſs you of that precious Legacy which our dying Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our left to his Diſciples, <hi>Peace I leave with you, my peace I give you;</hi> and will alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct you by the ſureſt method to <hi>that peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding.</hi> A
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105122:11"/>fourth duty which I think my ſelf more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly obliged to recommend to you, is <hi>Loyalty and Obedience to the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Give not way, I beſeech you, to any little uneaſineſſes, which the preſent circumſtances of affairs may lay upon ſome of you; do not murmur or repine at every diſappointment caſt not the blame of una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable miſcarriages, upon thoſe who are concerned in the management of affairs; but contentedly reſolve ſuch unexpected oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences into the over-ruling Providence of an All-wiſe God: Let nothing tempt you to <hi>ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> or laviſhly to cenſure the conduct of your Governors: be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to think, that God can chuſe for you as well as your ſelves, and pay a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obedience to the King he has ſet over you, who conſents to bear the burthen of a war in his perſon, which touches you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in your purſes; contribute readily to the ſupport of thoſe Forces, which are well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to keep the danger from your doors; and think not much to give ſome part of your fortune for the ſecurity of the reſt,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105122:12"/>and your Religion into the bargain. Then will God give his bleſſing to you as the due reward of your ſubmiſſion to his Will, <hi>by whom Kings reign and Princes decree juſtice;</hi> and he himſelf will not fail to acknowledge that reſpect, which is paid to his image and his ſubſtitute. Theſe then are ſome of thoſe more uſeful duties, which whilſt you <hi>I commend you to the word of God's grace,</hi> I have thought fitting out of that to recommend to your practice; and may <hi>that word of grace</hi> ſo thrive within your hearts, that it may <hi>take root downwards, and bring forth fruit upwards;</hi> may it ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d abroad within your ſouls the more eminent graces and fruits of the ſpirit, ſuch as <hi>Humility, Charity a peaceable diſpoſition, and a hearty obedience to the Government which you live under; that ſo the good ſeed which has been carefully ſown</hi> which was <hi>plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and watered by my unworthy Miniſtry, may,</hi> by God's aſſiſtance; <hi>have a ſuitable encreaſe;</hi> and may not lie dead or ineffectual in any amongſt you, but produce; according to the ſeveral meaſures of his grace, <hi>in ſome a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d-fold, in ſome ſixty fold, in ſome thirty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105122:12"/>fold.</hi> This will <hi>commend you</hi> more ſucceſsfully <hi>to God,</hi> than all my endeavours are capable without it, and will both be able of <hi>itſelf to build you up here, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> here after to give you an inheritance among all them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> I ſhall briefly conſider theſe two great advantages, which our due regard t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the word of Gods grace,</hi> is here ſaid to be able to impart unto us, and then I ſhall make haſte to a concluſion. And</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. A due regard to the <hi>word of Gods grace, is able to build us up.</hi> This is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor taken from a Houſe, and it gives us to underſtand thus much, that in order to our deſerving the commendation, of being <hi>built up by the word of Gods grace,</hi> there are two neceſſary qualifications required, without which no edifice can be thought compleat; and thoſe are a foundation and a ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture: that which in a ſpiritual building an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the former of theſe, is faith; and that which is agreeable to the latter, is a good life and converſation; for, to believe rightly, and to act accordingly, comprehends the whole duty of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105122:13"/>1ſt then, I ſay, in this ſpiritual building, there muſt be faith as a foundation. God, who is a <hi>wiſe</hi> and skilful <hi>Maſter-builder,</hi> will not allow his Houſe to be <hi>built upon the ſand,</hi> but takes care to <hi>have it founded upon a rock;</hi> as knowing that a failure in that principal part, can never be redreſſed by any thing done afterwards: let the other parts be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged with never ſo much care, let them be beautified and adorned with never ſo much coſt, yet cannot all this make amends for the firſt miſcarriage; it will be but a gayety of ſhort ſtanding, overwhelm'd by the violence of the firſt ſtorm that ſhocks it: Unleſs our faith be <hi>ſtedfaſt and unmoveable,</hi> unleſs it be ſettled beyond wavering and doubtfulneſs, it will never be able to ſuſtain the weight of thoſe good works which muſt be raived upon it: But <hi>the word of Gods grace,</hi> the Goſpel of our Saviour, is able to fix our faith ſo firmly and unalterably, as that it ſhall be ſubject <hi>to no variableneſs, neither ſhadow of turning:</hi> it carries with it ſuch a power of conviction, and the divine autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhines through it ſo clearly, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105122:13"/>attends to it ſeriouſly and without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, muſt needs be convinced by <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the ſpirit;</hi> and therefore, my brethren, if any amongſt you find their ſaith at any time to be tottering and unſteady, I <hi>commend you</hi> then eſpecially <hi>to the word of Gods grace,</hi> apply your ſelves to it with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt aſſiduity; and God, who is never want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe, who are not firſt neglectful of him and of themſelves, will not fail to aſſiſt you with ſuch a portion of his Spirit, as will enable you to profit by that, and will make that <hi>able to build you up.</hi> But as this ſpiritual building muſt in the firſt place have faith for its foundation, ſo muſt it</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Have a good life and converſation for the ſuperſtructure. A foundation is but uſeleſs of it ſelf, and only ſuppoſes the folly of the undertaker, unleſs he proceeds to compleat the work, and finiſhes the upper ſtories for ornament and uſe; and thus faith alſo is dead and inſignificant, and ſerves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enhance the guilt of him that has it, unleſs it be made the ground-work of good actions, and has a happy influence upon the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105122:14"/>courſe of our whole life. Our Saviour tells us, <hi>that when any man begins to build a tower, he ought to compute whether he have ſufficient to finiſh it; leſt haply after he have laid the foundation, and is not able to finiſh it, all that behold it begin to mock him:</hi> and it is upon this very occaſion, that he ſpeaks this ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant parable, namely to expoſe the folly of thoſe men who attempt to enter upon a courſe of piety, and are not ſo far maſters of their reſolutions as to go through with it, and perſevere in it to the end. Theſe men perhaps are willing to give their aſſent to all the myſteries contained in the Goſpel to confeſs the truth of whatever it affects, and not to call in queſtion the equity of any of its doctrines; and this they think is ſufficient for them, without ever applying themſelves to the practice of thoſe duties, which it ſtrictly requires of all believers; they are contented indeed to be ſpeculative Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but it is upon the condition that they may be practical Atheiſts; but this deſerves no better a character, than <hi>the knowing, of our Maſters will without the doing</hi> it, and we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105122:14"/>that the conſequence of that ſhall <hi>be many ſtripes.</hi> In vain then ſhall we plead, that we believe the Goſpel; in vain ſhall we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow our ſelves to be profeſſors of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, unleſs our practice be anſwerable to our profeſſion, and our faith is manifeſted by our works; our Saviour will declare <hi>that he knows us not,</hi> and will ſay to us, <hi>depart from me ye workers of iniquity:</hi> we may make our paſſionate addreſſes at the door, and with repeated exclamations cry, <hi>Lord, Lord, open unto us;</hi> but we ſhall be turned away as the fooliſh Virgins were, becauſe <hi>our Lamps</hi> have not been <hi>filled and trim'd.</hi> But the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt is ſuch <hi>a light unto our ſteps, and lantern to our paths,</hi> as if we attend to it with a becoming reverence, will <hi>direct our feet into the ways of godlineſs:</hi> we ſhall there ſee, if we are not willfully blind, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of our Saviours coming into the world, was not barely to inform our underſtanding, but chiefly and moſt eſpecially to regulate out practice; that his buſineſs was not to form a ſet of Diſputants; who ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and wrangle about points of controverſy,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105122:15"/>but <hi>to purifie to himſelf a peculiar people zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good works:</hi> it will convince us that all the promiſes of the Goſpel, all the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious overtures which it exhibits, have this expreſs condition annexed unto them, that we lead a pious and a godly life. When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever therefore, my Brethren, at any time you find your ſelves in danger to be miſled by your luſts, into the commiſſion of any groſs enormity, <hi>I then</hi> eſpecially <hi>commend you to the word of Gods grace;</hi> and adviſe you to betake your ſelves to that ſet of Sacred Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which will give you ſuch aſſiſtance as may baffle your temptations, and prove it ſelf <hi>able to build you up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there is, ſecondly, another advantage, which a due regard to the <hi>word of God's grace</hi> is here ſaid to be able to impart unto you, <hi>it is able</hi> (ſays the Text) <hi>to give you an inheritance among all them which are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is an advantage of ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a value, as is ſufficient to engage you to a due regard, if the <hi>word of God's grace</hi> had nothing elſe to recommend it. <hi>To have an
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105122:15"/>inheritance among all them which are ſanctified,</hi> and to ſhare in that poſſeſſion which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for Gods Elect, what a noble privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ought this to be eſteemed, and how zealouſly ſhould you contend to qualifie your ſelves for it! There are two things conſiderable in the deſcription of it. 1. That it is ſaid to be <hi>an inheritance:</hi> and 2. That it is ſuch <hi>among all them which are ſanctified.</hi> 1. then, It is ſaid to be <hi>an inheritance;</hi> and this ſhews you the certainty of that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the ſureſt tenure is that of inheritance; and eſpecially amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> it was looked upon as a thing ſacred, and not to be alienated upon any occaſion: thus <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> choſe rather to expoſe himſelf to the King's anger, and to that unjuſt proſecution which coſt him his life, than he would tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs againſt this ſolemn cuſtom, by parting with the Vineyard which he deſired; <hi>the Lord forbid it me</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that I ſhould give thee the inheritance of my fathers.</hi> Yet this ſecure and unalterable title is that by which you are allowed to make your claim; and it is upon a due regard <hi>to the word of Gods grace,</hi> that the right we pretend to is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105122:16"/>and eſtabliſhed; it is that which gives you the happy aſſurances of your being <hi>heirs of God, and co-heirs with Chriſt;</hi> from thence you gain <hi>that ſpirit of adoption, by which you cry Abba, Father;</hi> and if you are led by the directions which that gives, you ſhall find <hi>your ſelves thereby made members of that general Aſſembly and Church of the firſt born, whoſe names are written and regiſtered in heaven;</hi> and happily admitted to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon partakers of the <hi>glorious liberty of the children of God.</hi> But 2dly, This is <hi>an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among all them which are ſanctified.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is unclean can gain any admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance into this moſt holy and immaculate fellowſhip; purity of life is the only qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by which you may be fitted for this bleſſed ſociety: Thoſe who would be looked upon as the brethren of Chriſt, muſt put on him, and wear his reſemblance; and <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever has his hope in him, muſt purify himſelf even as he is pure.</hi> This is what <hi>the word of God's grace,</hi> inculcates to you almoſt in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry page: <hi>he that will aſcend into the hill of the Lord and abide in his holy place, muſt have clean hands and a pure heart;</hi> if you expect
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105122:16"/>
               <hi>that God ſhould be a father unto you, and that you ſhould he his ſons and daughters, you muſt come out from among the wicked and be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and not touch the unclean thing: having therefore theſe promiſes, dearly beloved, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the ſear of God.</hi> Thus if you give a careful attention, to theſe and ſuch other rules and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are every where contain'd in <hi>the word of Gods grace,</hi> you will find that ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſecure to you theſe advantages, you will <hi>find it able to give you an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all them which are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus in a confuſed and indigeſted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (ſuch as my preſent concern will give me leave to make uſe of) I have touch'd upon all the material obſervations, which the words of my Text have furniſhed me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and having all along applied them to your more particular uſe, I ſhall add nothing more to what I have ſaid already. I ſhall only offer up, as I am in diſpenſably obliged, by all the ties of gratitude and duty, my moſt hearty prayers to Almighty God, that he would ſanctify to you all what I have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105122:17"/>now been preaching, and what at any time heretofore I have delivered to you; that ſo being defended <hi>by the protection of your God,</hi> and fully inſtructed by the <hi>word of his grace,</hi> you may <hi>be built up</hi> and eſtabliſhed in your holy profeſſion here, and <hi>have your inheritance hereafter among all them which are ſanctified</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave to conclude the whole with St <hi>Paul</hi>'s exhortation to his <hi>Corinthians: Finally, brethren, farewel be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you.</hi> To him the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, three perſons but one God of love, be aſcribed all honour, power, might, majeſty and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, henceforth and for evermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="by_the_same_author">
            <head>
               <hi>Sermons Preached by the Reverend Mr.</hi> Brady, <hi>and Sold by</hi> R. Parker.</head>
            <p>A Sermon preached at <hi>Helmingham</hi> in <hi>Suffolk, June</hi> 30th, 1694. At the Funeral of Lieutenant General <hi>Talmach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at <hi>Whitehall, March</hi> 3d. 1695. upon occaſion of her late Majeſty's Death, before the Right Honourable the Counteſs of <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> and the reſt of the Mourning Ladies.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at the Pariſh-Church of <hi>St. Martins Ludgate, Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb.</hi> 12th. 1695. before the Incorporated Society of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at St. <hi>Catherine Cree-Church,</hi> upon <hi>Sunday</hi> the 1ſt of <hi>March</hi> 1696. upon occaſion of the late horrid Plot.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105122:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
